A Guide to the Friends of the Stone House at Harper Park Papers, 1996-2009
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Friends of the Stone House at Harper Park Papers 1996-2009
Thomas Balch Library
M 057
The collection consists of three boxes containing material saved by Joan Rokus concerning Friends of the Stone House at Harper Park. They are filed alphabetically by folder titles Rokus used. Some records such as minutes, committee reports, staff reports, correspondence, etc. are incomplete. The collection includes architectural plans drawn by John Milner Associates, Inc. of Alexandria, Virginia with that firm's estimated costs for the proposed work. There is a plat of the property dated August 10, 2001. That survey was done by Patton Harris Rust Associates of Leesburg, Virginia. There are also photographs of Lafayette Day on September 2, 2000, presentation of a painting of the building to the Harper Park Middle School, and of a presentation made at the Loudoun campus of George Washington University. There are also miscellaneous photographs of the building under construction and of the finished exterior.
Joan Rokus, Friends of the Stone House at Harper Park, Leesburg, VA
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Joan Rokus, Friends of the Stone House at Harper Park, Leesburg, VA
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2009.0139
Historical Information
The Stone House at Harper Park, built in 1822, was initially used as an ordinary. The building subsequently served as a tenant house and, eventually, a gift shop in the 1960s before being vacant for many years. The house, and the tract of land on which it stood, changed hands many times. By the 1960s, the house and land belonged to the Hamblet family. They donated the house to Loudoun County in 1968 to be used as a tourist information center, but the Board of Supervisors returned it in 1971 because of concerns about cost and transportation.
On 28 March 1996, William Randall Hamblet, Susan Swink Hamblet, his wife, Susan Harper Hamblet, and Matthew Lewis Hamblet signed a Memorandum of Understanding with the Board of Supervisors of Loudoun County. The memorandum conveyed a parcel containing the Stone House to the County of Loudoun. The gift stipulated that the building and its immediate surroundings be used as a "park housing a museum and/or tourist information center." The building was to be moved to another parcel, also owned by the donors, at no expense to the donors and this was accomplished.
Joan Rokus, a former Loudoun County supervisor, became interested in preserving the building when the development of the Harper Park subdivision threatened the building's survival. She helped found Friends of the Stone House at Harper Park in 1996. In 1998, the Virginia State Corporation Commission issued a charter and the group adopted bylaws. The stated purpose of the organization was to support the reconstruction, occupancy, maintenance and preservation of the historic structure known as the Stone House at Harper Park. The organization achieved 501c3 status in May of 2004 which enabled it to receive tax exempt donations.
Rokus was the guiding force and first president of the board of Friends of the Stone House at Harper Park. The board worked closely with the county through the staff of the Department of Parks and Recreation. Plans for the restoration of the Stone House were drawn by John Milner Associates, Inc. of Alexandria, Virginia in 2001. Friends of the Stone House at Harper Park sought funding from various organizations, and in 2004 it was awarded $100,000 in federal funding through the Transportation Equity Act for the Twenty-First Century. There were also smaller grants from other organizations such as the Loudoun Restoration and Preservation Society and from businesses and individuals.
Despite these grants the board of the Friends of the Stone House realized that the funds were not going to be sufficient to complete the restoration work and make the house usable for the purpose designated in the deed of gift by the date set by the donors. The Loudoun County Board of Supervisors was also becoming concerned about the mounting costs. After considerable correspondence with the donors it was decided to give the property back to them. The remaining money was given to several historical and preservation societies in the county.
The Loudoun County Board of Supervisors held a public hearing on November 13, 2007 to consider conveying the property to the donors. A letter in box 1, folder 13 indicates that the property was conveyed back to the family on that date. However, the final disbursement of the organization's funds did not take place until 2009 as noted in the agenda for a meeting of the "Friends, Advisors, and guests." The date of this meeting was not given but the agenda was sent, apparently by e-mail, on April 19, 2009.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of three boxes containing material saved by Joan Rokus concerning Friends of the Stone House at Harper Park. They are filed alphabetically by folder titles Rokus used. Some records such as minutes, committee reports, staff reports, correspondence, etc. are incomplete.
The property was given to the Board of Supervisors of Loudoun County by deed of subdivision and of gift on 28 March 1996 by William Randall Hamblet and Susan Swink Hamblet, his wife; Susan Harper Hamblet; and Matthew Lewis Hamblet, but there is no written record of the founding of Friends of the Stone House. The earliest document noting the existence of Friends of the Stone House is a 1999 list of nine members with a handwritten notation that it does not include the board of directors or the advisory board members. This indicates that the group was already organized even though there were few members. There follow lists of the boards for the years 2000, 2001, 2002, and 2003.
The collection includes architectural plans drawn by John Milner Associates, Inc. of Alexandria, Virginia with that firm's estimated costs for the proposed work. There is a plat of the property dated August 10, 2001. That survey was done by Patton Harris Rust Associates of Leesburg, Virginia. There are also photographs of Lafayette Day on September 2, 2000, presentation of a painting of the building to the Harper Park Middle School, and of a presentation made at the Loudoun campus of George Washington University. There are also miscellaneous photographs of the building under construction and of the finished exterior.
Arrangement
Box: Folder
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Friends of the Stone House at Harper Park Papers (M 057), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Memorandum of Understanding. Deed Book 1443, page 0940. Office of the Clerk of the Circuit Court of Loudoun County.
Other Finding Aid
None
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
Lewis/Edwards file 53-0254, Harper Stone House; Lewis/Edwards file 53-0256, Carrodoc Hall
Separated Material
None
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - Agendas, Board of Directors, 2001-2004
  - Annual Meeting Agendas, 2001-2002
  - Advisory Board information
  - Architects' proposals
  - Architect's plans (#1), John Milner Associates, Inc. and plat of the property, 2001
  - Architect's plans (#2)
  - Articles of Incorporation
  - August Court Days, 2002-2003
  - Board of Directors
  - Brochures
  - Committees, 2002
  - Construction, 2001, 2003, 2004
  - Convention and Visitors' Center workshop
  - Correspondence, 2001- 2007
  - Deed of Gift, March 28, 1996
  - Dissolution of deed of gift, 2009
- (Box 2)
  - Environmental and Historic Resources, 2000-2003
  - Events, 2002-2003
  - Expenses
  - Fundraising #1
  - Fundraising #2: TEA 21 grants
  - Hamblet, Matthew
  - Heritage Consortium
  - Historic Information
  - History
  - Holiday Inn (Carradoc Hall)
  - Lafayette program
  - Leesburg
  - Mailing lists
  - Memorandum of Understanding with Hamblet family
  - Mission Statement
- (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 2000-2004
  - Parliamentarian
  - Photographs #1: Lafayette Day, 2 September 2000
  - Photographs#2: presentation of painting to Harper Park Middle School
  - Photographs #3: miscellaneous
  - Photographs #4: presentation at Loudoun Campus of George Washington University
  - Photograph: old photograph when it was a dwelling, n.d.
  - President's reports, 2001-2004
  - Publicity #1
  - Publicity #2
  - Staff reports, 2001-2005
  - Tax free status
  - Timelines, 1998-2001
  - Treasurer's reports
  - Virginia Department of Historic Resources
  - Virginia Tech, work at stone house, 1999
  - Volunteers